thank you for joining me the real Howard
Yates with speaking in drums here on
YouTube and also part of my podcast I'm
gonna talk about one of the products
that I've just recently purchased and
actually got to try out this past
Saturday night this is a drum company a
stick company that I've wanted to go
with for a very long time and for some
reason just never got around to doing it
so the stick company is vader for years
I've been using either Zildjian or vic
firth occasionally using pro mark not
really a big fan of their stuff so the
one that I tried out and I've got
actually a couple of different pair that
I really like for different reasons
they're both fairly heavy the one I'm
gonna talk about today is the fat back
model 3a if you can see it right there
oh yeah this is a fairly weighty stick
and I'm used to playing larger sticks
because of well for when I was in
marching band for several years and I
did a play snare and we used the Ralph
Hartman drumsticks back them from Vic
Firth it was solid white they had the
white nylon tip and those are how we
basically cut our teeth and also busted
our our ring finger right there with the
traditional grip those many band-aids
and lots of rawness from from that time
period those summers where we went back
to playing I had took a little time
getting used to those particular sticks
but I love them and I love the weight
and I think a lot of it has to do with
it with that concept of the weight
itself I think can determine how much
work I actually have to do and I find
that with a lighter stick it seems like
I have to focus more I have to use more
muscle and in finer muscles too so I'm
having to concentrate a little bit more
it just seems like a lot more work for
me and I can't seem to relax let the
stick do its work so even when I'm
playing fast music I typically will use
practically the same type of drumsticks
so I mean it doesn't seem economically
sound it doesn't seem like the right way
that maybe Bob Ross or somebody would
paint something
obviously if you wanted to do something
you'd use the the big brush that he'd
beat the devil out of or he'd use a fan
brush to do certain things that get
certain certain parts of the spruce
trees to turn out the way they do or the
or using the little little scraper there
to get the parts of the snowdrifts on
the mountaintops to look a certain way
so I mean there's you can look at
drumming in that aspect of using certain
tools for the job for certain songs and
styles and and applications in tempo but
for me I'm fairly comfortable with using
typically heavier sticks I think I just
physically like the feel of having to
either put a little more physicality
into it a little more effort more work
but also I find that even if I'm playing
faster stuff and again it's just me it's
a preference it's just my style but I
also find that with some of these
thicker larger drum sticks that they do
a lot of the work for me so I don't have
to play as much or put as much behind
them sometimes so I can actually kind of
relax a little bit and you know a lot of
that comes from the fact that I play the
lounge metal and you know a lot of that
comes from the fact that I play lounge
metal which means I play in really loud
places with loud instruments and it's
ridiculous it really is there's some
venues that we shouldn't even be playing
at but we get asked to come back and
then we're asked to turn down every
single time and oh my god so anyhow the
fatback 3a Vader there it is right there
oh yeah all right so this stick here
again pretty beefy and it doesn't it
surprisingly doesn't weigh that much
it's I wouldn't say that it has a hollow
feel to it I don't know how to describe
it like it seems like it's hollow but
it's not if it plays like it's a full
thick piece of wood like it's of just
one solid piece which it is but
sometimes with a certain feel of some
sticks
they feel that they're lighter and this
one has kind of a light feel but I like
the fact that it has such like a pretty
beefy neck and that barrel tip is pretty
big if you ever look at the ones from
like the Steve Gadd or the Dave Weckl
models from Vic Firth those are light or
even like the Peter Erskine which is
even smaller than those they have a
little bead a barrel tip but this one is
actually quite big and I really had no
problems because of that
with any stick definition on the bell
the ride cymbal or anything like that
and considering I took these up for a
test spin this weekend and I doubt you
can see it but I don't have that many
marks on here and this is actually the
one I probably primarily use in my right
hand the other one has some stick marks
in it as well as you might be able to
see maybe maybe not but they're not
terribly chipped or anything like that
and part of it is how you angle your
cymbals and how hard you play and
whether or not you let somebody else use
your drumsticks and they break them
thank you which has happened to me
recently somebody decided to take my
signature Mike Portnoy now again I know
he's Pro mark very often not a big fan
of them but the ones that I do like are
the Mike Portnoy signature sticks the
420 models and I had an old set that
were that had like the purple lavender
pink kind of like paint on them took him
to a gig to play on somebody else's drum
set and then somehow or another those
thick's ended up in the hands of
somebody else during the transition of
all these different drummers and I go
back to the set at the end of the night
and find that one of those thick's is
literally broken in half so whoever did
that you're an thanks there was
no need for that
those thick's were in perfectly good
condition before you did that so piss
off you have keeping it PC here kids so
I'm very happy with this particular set
of sticks fatback I had pretty good
control over them the one thing I don't
know about vader drum sticks is if
they're anything like Vic Firth where
Vic Firth claims they have some sort of
a wax that heats up in your hands so it
kind of creates a tacky surface those
are the words of Vic Firth on a video
that I watched I find myself doing this
a lot so kind of just doing that for me
to kind of get my own sort of grip going
I also like to use the Vader well I mean
there's there's different companies that
have them too but the the grip tape that
goes around right I like using that
because that even makes me feel like I
don't have to even put that much of a
grip on it it's again it's sort of like
letting the instrument or the stick
itself do the work and having the grip
tape on there does the same thing for me
but the fat back I think fits my hands
quite well overall is very impressed
with the dynamic ability again it is a
very thick drum stick again very thick
barrel tip but surprisingly a little
light but when I soon as I played them
on the pads when I took him for a test
spin at Guitar Center when nobody was
around okay I never gotten back to that
part about how I got to the drum stick
so you have to go behind the counter
apparently when there's nobody there
nobody was there for 20 minutes or so no
other person showed up no customers no
body and they've put the sticks behind
the counter so I went around the counter
which I guess I'm not supposed to do but
hey I have to get the drum sticks right
I go back there and it's blocked off by
a wedge monitor and an entire electronic
drum kit so I have to stand on like one
foot take one hand and lean over the
electronic kit and start randomly
reaching for sticks me this is how
ridiculous this was I was just randomly
grabbing stuff trying to kid try to find
a pair of sticks that I can use so then
I try them hack out on the pad and
everything
so but I settle on these and was very
happy with them I would suggest trying
these out if you get a chance if you
find a store that has them or if you
find a Guitar Center that has the
drumsticks behind the counter just go
ahead and go back there and get them and
try them out because nobody's gonna help
you get them for you the only reason I
checked out is because I played on the
pads for about a good 10 to 15 minutes
afterwards and somebody finally showed
up and decided that we're gonna cash me
out so I'm very pleased with these I
will continue to use them until further
notice and hopefully I can keep them as
good of shape as I did with these and
again I play three for our shows so this
for a first run is actually really good
both them look about the same roughly
but a pretty durable stick not too heavy
but not too light either kind of a
medium weight but a fixed stick with a
big thick barrel tip very happy with
that so I'm Howard Yates for speaking in
drums I'll see you later